Oh hello, and welcome to lesson three of practical deep learning for coders
We
Were looking at
getting our model into production last week and
So we're going to finish off that today and then we're going to start to look behind the scenes at what actually goes on when?
We train a neural network. We're going to look at
Kind of the math of what's going on
And we're going to learn about SGD and it's important stuff like that
The the order is slightly different to the book in the book
there's a part in the book which says like hey, you can either go to
Lesson 4 or lesson 3 now and then go back to the other one afterwards. So we're doing lesson 4 and then lesson 3
Chapter 4 and then chapter 3 I should say
You can choose it
Whichever way you're interested in
Chapter 4 is the more technical chapter about the foundations of how deep learning really works whereas chapter 3 is all about
ethics
And so with the lessons we'll do that next week
So we're looking at
0-2 production notebook and
We've got to look at the fast book version to run with her and in fact everything
I'm looking at today will be in the fast book version and
Remember last week. We had a look at
Our our bears and we created this data loaders object
by using
The datablock api which I hope everybody's had a chance to experiment with this week if you haven't now's a good time to do it
We kind of skipped over one of the lines a little bit
Item transforms so what this is doing here when we said resize
The the images we downloaded from the internet had lots of different sizes and lots of different aspect ratios
Some at all and some are wide. I'm a square and some are big some are small
When you say resize for an item transform, it means each item to an item in this case is one image
Is going to be resized to 128 by 128
By squishing it or stretching it. And so we had a look at you can always say show batch to see a few examples and
This is what they look like
Squishing and stretching isn't the only way that we can resize remember we have everything we have to make everything into a square
Before we kind of get it into our model by the time it gets to our model
Everything has to be the same size in each mini wedge. So that's why and they're making it a square
It's not the only way to do that, but it's the easiest way and it's the by far the most common way
um, so
Another way to do this
Is we can create a another
Data block object and we can make a data block object
That's an identical copy of an existing data block object where we can then change just some pieces
And we can do that by calling the new method which is super handy. And so let's create another data block
object in this time with different item transform where we resize
using the
Squish method we have a question. What are the advantages of having Square images versus rectangular ones?
That's a great question so
Really its simplicity
Yeah, if if you know
All of your images are rectangular of a particular aspect ratio to start with you may as well
Just keep them that way but if you've got some which at all and some which are wide
Making them all square is kind of the easiest
Otherwise, you would have to kind of organize them such as all of the tall ones kind of ended up in a mini batch nor
The wide ones ended up in a mini batch
And then you'd have to kind of then figure out
What the best aspect ratio for each mini batch is and we actually have some research that does that in fast AI too
But it's still a bit clunky
I should mention. Okay, I just lied to you. The default is not actually to squish your stretch the default
I should have said sorry the default when we say resize is actually just to
grab
Grab the center
Actually, all we're doing is regretting the center of each image
so if we want to squish your stretch
You can add the resize method squish argument to resize and you can now see that this black bear is now looking much thinner
But we have got the kind of leaves that are round on each side instance
Another question when you use the DL s dot new method what can cannot be changed is it just the
Transforms it so it's not dl s new it's bears dot new right? So we're not creating a new data Lotus object
We're creating a new data block object. I don't remember off the top of my head
so check the documentation and I'm sure somebody can pop the answer into the
into the form
So
you can see when we use dot squish that this grizzly bear is got
pretty kind of
Wide and weird-looking and this black bear has got pretty weird and thin looking and it's easiest kinda to see what's going on
if we use
Precise method pad and what dot pad does as you can see is it just add some?
Black bars around each side so you can see the grizzly bear was tall
So then when we we stretched squashing and stretching opposites of each other
So when we stretched it, it ended up wide and the black bear was
Originally a wide rectangle. So it ended up looking kind of thin
To use zero zeros means pad it with black you can also say like reflect to kind of have
The pixels will kind of look a bit better that way if you use reflect
All of these different methods have their own problems
The the pad method is kind of the cleanest you end up with the correct size you end up with all of the pixels
But you also end up with wasted pixels. So you kind of end up with wasted computation
This grish method is the most efficient because you get all of the information
You know and and nothing's kind of wasted but on the downside your neural nets gonna have to learn to kind of like
Recognize when something's being squished or stretched and in some cases, it might it wouldn't even know
So if there's two objects
You're trying to recognize one of which tends to be thin and one of it tends to be thick in other words
They're the same. They could actually be impossible to distinguish
And then the default cropping approach
Actually removes some information. So in this case
You know, this is grizzly bear here
We actually lost a lot of its legs. So if figuring it out what kind of bear it was
Required looking at its feet. Well, we don't have its feet anymore
So they all have downsides
So there's something else that you can do a different approach which is instead us to say resize you can say
Random resized crop and actually, this is the most common approach and what random resize crop does is each time
It actually grabs a
Different part of the image and kind of zooms into it. Alright, so
these this is all the same image and we're just grabbing a batch of
four different versions of it and you can see some are kind of
you know, they're all squished in different ways and we've kind of selected different subsets and so forth now this
Panna seems worse than any of the previous approaches because I'm losing information like this one here
I've actually lost a whole lot of its of its back, right?
but the cool thing about this is that remember we want to avoid overfitting and
When you see a different part of the animal each time
It's much less likely to over fit because you're not seeing the same image on each
Epoch that you go around that makes sense. So
So this random random resized crop approach is actually super popular and so min scale 0.3 means
We're going to pick at least
30% of the pixels of kind of the original size each time
And then what kind of like zoom into that that square?
So
This idea of doing something so that each time the model sees the image. It looks a bit different to last time
It's called data augmentation. And this is one type of data augmentation. It's
Probably the most common
But there are others
and
one of the best ways to do a data augmentation is to use
this
transforms function and what all transforms does is it actually returns a list of
Different
augmentations and so there are
augmentations which change contrast which change brightness
Which warps a perspective so you can see in this one here
it looks like this bits much closer to you and this moves much away from you because it's going to be in perspective what it
Rotates them see this one's actually being rotated. This one's been made really dark, right?
These are batch transforms not item transforms. The difference is that item transforms happen one image at a time?
And so the thing that resizes them all of the same size that has to be an item transform
Pop it all into a mini batch
put it on the GPU and then a batch transform happens to a whole mini batch at a time and
by putting these as batch transforms that the augmentation happens super fast because it happens on the GPU and
I don't know if there's any other
Libraries as we speak which allow you to write your own GPU accelerated transformations that run on the GPU in this way
so this is a super handy thing in first AI to
So you can check out the documentation or
Org transforms and when you do you'll find the documentation for all of the underlying transforms that it basically wraps, right?
So you can see if I shift tab
I don't remember for showing you this trick before if you go inside the parentheses of a function and hit shift tab a few times
it'll pop open a list of all of the arguments and so you can basically see you can say like oh
Can I sometimes flip it left? Right? Can I sometimes flip it up down? What's the maximum and I can rotate zoom?
range Allah lighting
What the perspective?
and so forth
How can we add different augmentations for train and validation sets?
So the cool thing is that
Automatically last a I will avoid doing data augmentation on the validation set
so all of these all transforms will only be applied to
the
Training set
with the exception of random resize crop random resize crop has a different behavior or each
The behavior for the training set is what we just saw which is to randomly pick a subset. I'm going to zoom into it and
the
Behavior for the validation set is just to grab the center the largest center square that it can
You can write your own
Transformations that they're just Python they just standard pi torch code
the way if you and and by default it will only be applied to
The training set if you want to do something fancy
Like random resize crop where you actually have different things being applied to H
You should come back to the next course to find out how to do that or read the documentation. It's not rocket science, but it's
That's something most people need to do
Um, okay, so
Last time we
Did bears dot new with a random resize crop mean scale of 0.5. We added some transforms
And he went ahead and trained actually since last week over rerun this notebook
I've got it's on a different computer and I've got different images. So it's not all exactly the same
but I still got a good confusion matrix of the
37 were classified correctly to a Grizzly's of one was a teddy
Now
Plot plot top losses and it's interesting you can see in this case
There's some clearly kind of odd things going on. This is not a bear at all
This looks like it's a drawing of a bear which it's decided is
Predicted as a Teddy, but this thinks it's meant to be a drawing of a black bear. I can certainly see the confusion
You can see
How some parts would have been cut off, but talk about how to deal with that later
Now one of the interesting things is that we didn't really do much
Data cleaning at all before we built this model
The only data cleaning we did was just to validate that each image can be opened there. Was that verify images call
and the reason for that is it's actually much easier normally to clean your data after you create a model and I'll show you how
We've got this thing called
image classifier cleaner
Where you can pick a category, right?
and
training set or validation set
And then what it will do is it will then
List all of the images in that set and it will pick the ones
which are
The which is the least confident about which is the most likely to be wrong
Where the weather loss is the worst to be more precise
and so this
this is a great way to
Look through your data and find problems. So in this case the first one
Is not a teddy or a brown bear or a black bear. It's a puppy dog
All right. So this is a great cleaner because what I can do is I can now click delete here
This one here looks a bit like an Ewok rather than a teddy. I'm not sure. What do you think Rachel isn't an Ewok?
I'm going to call it an Ewok
Ok, and so you can kind of go through
Okay, that's definitely not a teddy and so you can either say like oh that's wrong it's actually a grizzly bear or it's wrong
it's a black bear or I should delete it or by default is keep it right and you can kind of keep going through until
You think like okay, they're all seem to be fine
Maybe that one's not
Kind of once you get to the point where they also in to be fine, you can kind of say, okay
Probably all the rest to fine too because they all have lower losses. So they all fit the kind of the mold of a teddy
And so then I can run this code here
Where I just go through cleaner, dr. Leach so that's all the things which I've selected delete for and unlink them so unlink
Is just another way of saying delete a file that's the Python name
And then go through all the ones that we said change and we can actually move them to the correct
directory
If you haven't seen this before you might be surprised that we've kind of created our own little gooey inside
Jupiter notebook
Yeah, you can do this and we built this with less than a screen of code you can check out the source code in the
Past AI notebooks. So this is a great time to remind you that
This is a great time to remind you that
Ji
is built with notebooks and so if you go to the first AI repo and clone it and then go to NBS you'll find
all of the code of fast AI
Written as notebooks and they've got a lot of prose and examples and tests and so forth
So the best place to learn about how this is implemented is to look at the notebooks
rather than looking at the
module code
Okay
By the way, sometimes you'll see like weird little comments like this
These weird little comments are part of a development environment for Jupiter notebook
we use called env dev which we built so
Silva and I built this thing to make it much easier for us to kind of create books
And websites and libraries in Jupiter notebooks. So this particular one here hide
means
when this is turned into a book or into documentation don't show this cell and
The reason for that is because you can see I've actually got it in the text, right?
But I thought when you're actually running it, it would be nice to have it sitting here waiting for you to run directly
So that's why it's shown in the notebook. But not in the in the book has shown differently
Like s : with a quote in the book that would end up saying
Sylvia says and then what he says so there's kind of little bits and pieces in the
In the notebooks that just look a little bit odd
And that's because it's designed that way in order to show in order to create stuff in them
Right, so then last week we saw how you can export that to a pickle file that contains all the information from the model
And then on the server where you're going to actually do your inference
You can then load that save file and you'll get back a learner that you can call predict on so predict
Perhaps the most interesting part of predict is the third thing that it returns
Which is a tensor in this case containing three numbers
But the three numbers there's three of them because we have three classes teddy bear grizzly bear and black bear. All right, and so
This doesn't make any sense until you know what the order of the classes is kind of in in
in your data loaders
And you can ask the data loaders what the order is by asking for its vocab
So a vocab in fast AI is a really common concept
it's basically any time that you've got like a mapping from numbers to strings or
Discrete levels. The mapping is always taught in the vocab. So here this shows us that the
The activation or
Black bear is
Six the activation for grizzly is one and the activation for teddy is ten a neck six
So very very confident that this particular one it was a grizzly not surprisingly this was something called grizzly type JPEG
Um
This
This mapping in order to display the correct thing
But of course the data loaders object already knows that mapping and it's all the vocab and it's stored in with the loader
So that's how it knows to say grizzly automatically
So the first thing it gives you is the human readable string that you'd want to display
So this is kind of nice that with FASTA a to you you save this object which has everything you need for inference
It's got all the you know information about
Normalization about any kind of transformation steps about what the vocab is so it can display everything correctly
Right. So now we want to
Deploy this as an app
now if you've done some web programming before then all you need to know is that this
line of code and this line of code
so this is the line of codes you would call once when your application starts up and
Then this is the line of code you would call
Every time you want to do an inference, and there's also a batch version of it
Which you can look up if you're interested, this is just a Roo one at a time
So there's nothing special
If you're already a web programmer or have access to a web programmer
these that you don't you just have to stick these two lines of code somewhere and the three things you get back whether
The the human readable string if you're doing categorization
The index of that which in this case is one is grizzly and the probability of each plus
One of the things we really wanted to do in this course though is not assume that everybody is a web developer
most data scientists aren't but gee wouldn't it be great if all data scientists could at least like prototype an
application to show off the thing they're working on and
so we've
Trying to kind of curate an approach which none of its stuff. We've built. It's really as curated
Which shows how you can create a GUI and create a complete application in Jupiter notebook
so the
Key
Pieces of technology we use to do this our ipython widgets, which is always called a PI widgets and voila. I
pi widgets, which we import by default as widgets, and that's also what they use in their own documentation as
GUI widgets for example a file upload button
so if I create
this file upload button and then display it I
See and we saw this in the last lesson as well or maybe as lesson one an actual clickable button
so I can go ahead and
Click it
OK you've selected one thing. So how do I use that? Well these
While these widgets have all kinds of methods and properties and the upload button has a data property
Which is an array containing all of the images you uploaded
So you can pass that to Pio image create and so doc create is kind of the standard
Factory method we use in fast AI to create items
And Pol image create is smart enough to be able to create an item from all kinds of different things
And one of the things that can create it from is a binary blob which is what a file upload contains
so then we can display it and
There's our teddy, right?
So you can see how you know cells of Jupiter notebook can refer to other cells that were created that were kind of
have
GUI created data in them
Let's hide that teddy away for a moment and
the next thing to know about is that there's a kind of widget called output and an output widget is
It's basically something that
You can fill in later, right? So if I delete actually
This part here. So I've now got an output
widget
Access to this way around
And
You can't see the output widget, even though I said, please display it because nothing is output
So then in the next cell I can say with that output
householder
Display a thumbnail of the image and you'll see that the the display will not appear here
It appears back here, right? Because that's how that's where the placeholder was
So let's run that again to clear out that placeholder
So we can create another kind of placeholder which is a label their labels kind of a
Something where you can put text in it. They can give it a value like I don't know. Please choose an
image
Okay, so we've now got a label containing please choose an image
Let's create another button to do your classification
Now this is not a file upload button it's just a general button so this button doesn't do anything
all right, it doesn't do anything until we
Attach an event handler to it an event handler is a callback. We'll be learning all about callbacks in this course
if you've ever done any GUI programming before or even web programming you'll be familiar with the idea that you
Write a function, which is the thing you want to be called when the button is clicked on and then somehow you tell your framework
That this is the on click event
So here I go. Here's my button run. I
Say the on click event
the button run is
We call this code and this code is going to do all the stuff. We just saw and I create an image from the upload
It's going to clear the output. Let's play the image
call predict and then replace the
label with a prediction
There it all is now so that hasn't done anything but I can now go back to this classify button
Which now has an event handler attached to it. So watch this
quick
Pump and look that's been filled in
Filled in right in case you missed it. Let's run this again to clear everything out. Okay, everything's gone
This is please choose an image, there's nothing here I click classify
Well
Pop-up, right? So it's kind of amazing how our
Notebook has suddenly turned into this
interactive prototyping playground building applications and so once all this works
We can dump it all together. And so
The easiest way to dump things together is to create a V box
So V box is a vertical box
And it's just it's just something that you put widgets in
and so in this case
We're going to put the following widgets rhiness have a label that says select your beer
then an upload button a run button and output placeholder and a
label for predictions
But let's run these again just to clear everything out. So
That we're not cheating
And let's create our V box so as you can see it's just got all the
All the pieces
right
We've got whatever
I accidentally ran the thing that displayed the bear. Let's get rid of that
Okay, so there it is so now I can click upload my bear
Okay, and then I can click classify
right and notice I've this is exactly that this is this is like the same buttons as
These buttons they're like two places with we're viewing the same button, which is kind of a wild idea. So if I click classify
it's going to change this label and
This label because they're actually both references to the same label look
There we go
so
This is our app. Right? And so this is actually how I built that
that image planar GUI is
Just using these exact things and I built that image cleaner GUI
Cell-by-cell in a notebook just like this and so you get this kind of interactive
experimental framework
for building a GUI
so if you're a data scientist who's never done GUI stuff before this is a great time to get started because now you can
You can make actual
programs
now, of course an actual program
Running inside a notebook is kind of cool. But what we really want is this program to run in a place anybody can run it
That's where voila comes in Oh
Voila and needs to be installed so you can just run these lines
Or install it
It's listed in the prose
and one voila does is it takes a notebook and
Doesn't display anything except for the markdown
the ipython widgets and the outputs
Right, so well the code cells disappear and it doesn't give the person looking at that page the ability to run their own code
they can only
Interact with the widgets, right?
So what I did
was a copied and pasted that code from the notebook into a separate notebook, which only has
Those lines of code, right so
So this is just the same lines of code that we saw before
And so this is a notebook it's just a normal notebook
And then I installed voila and then when you do that if you
Navigate to this notebook but you replace
Notebooks up here with voila
It actually displays not the notebook but
Just as I said the markdown and the widgets so here I've got
Bear classifier and I can click upload. Let's do a grizzly bear this time
And this is a slightly different version I actually made this so there's no classify button
I thought it would be a bit more fancy to make it
So when you click upload it just runs everything but as you can see there it all is
Right. It's all working. So
This is the world's
simplest
Prototype, but it's it's a proof-of-concept right so you can add
widgets with
dropdowns and sliders and charts and you know everything that you can have in a
You know an angular app or a react app or whatever. And in fact, there's there's even
Stuff which lets you use, for example, the whole view j/s framework if you know that it's a very popular
JavaScript framework the whole view jes framework, you can actually use it in
widgets and voila
so now we want to get it so that this
this app
Can be run by
Someone out there in the world
So the voila documentation shows a few ways to do that, but perhaps the easiest one
Is to use a system called binder
So binder is at mine, but my binder org
And all you do is you paste in your github repository name here, right? And this is all in the book
So you
Could have repo name you change where it says
Pile we change that to URL
You can see and then you put in the path which we were just experimenting with
right
Pop that here and then you say launch and what that does is it then gives you a URL
So then this URL
You can pass on
to people
and this is actually your
interactive running application so binders free and so this is an you know,
Anybody can now use this to take their voila app and make it a publicly available web
application
So try it as it mentions here the first time you do this binder takes about five minutes
To build your site. Um
Because it actually uses something called docker to deploy the whole fast AI framework and Python and blah blah blah
But once you've done that
That virtual machine will keep running for you know, as long as people are using it. It'll keep running for a while
That virtual machine will keep running for a while as long as people are using it and you know, it's it's
reasonably fast
So a few things to note here
Being a free service. You won't be surprised to hear. This is not using a GPU is using a CPU
And so that might be surprising
But we're deploying to something which runs on a CPU
What do you think about it though, this makes much more sense to deploy to a CPU than a GPU
The
Just a moment
Um, the thing that's happening here is that I am
Passing along that let's go back to my app in my app. I'm passing along a single image at a time
So when I pass along that single image
I don't have a huge amount of parallel or work or a GPU to do
This is actually something that a CPU is going to be doing more efficiently
So we found that for folks coming through this course
The vast majority of the time they wanted to deploy
Inference on a CPU not a GPU because they're normally this doing one
item at a time
It's way cheaper and easier to deploy to a CPU
And the reason for that is that you can just use any
Hosting service you like because just remember this is just a this is just a program at this point, right?
And you can use all the usuals horizontal scaling vertical scaling, you know, you can use Heroku you can use AWS
You can use inexpensive instances
Super cheap and super easy
Having said that there are times you might need to deploy to a GPU
For example, maybe you're processing videos and so like a single video on on a CPU to process
It might take all day
or
You might be so successful that you have a thousand requests per second in
Which case you could like take?
128 at a time batch them together and put the whole batch on the GPU and get the results back and pass them back around
you gotta be careful of that right because
If your requests aren't coming fast enough your user has to wait for a whole batch of people to be ready to to be processed
But you know conceptually as long as your site is popular enough that could work
The other thing to talk about is you might want to deploy to a mobile phone
and
the point in to a mobile phone
Our recommendation is wherever possible
do that by actually deploying to a server and then have a mobile phone talk to the server over a network and
Because if you do that
Again, you can just use a normal pie torch program on a normal server and normal Network calls. It makes life super easy
When you try to run a PI torch app on a phone
You are suddenly now not an environment. We're not in an environment where like pi torch will run natively
and so you'll have to like convert your program into some other form and
There are other forms
And the the main form that you convert it to is something called Oh N and X which is specifically designed for
Kind of super high speed the high performance, you know
Approach that can run on both servers or on mobile phones and it does not require the whole
Python and pi torch kind of
runtime in place
but it's it's much more complex and
Not using it's harder to debug it. It's harder to set it up, but it's harder to maintain it. So
if possible keep things simple and
If you're lucky enough that you're so successful that you need to scale it up to GPUs or and stuff like that
then great, you know, hopefully you've got the the finances at that point to justify, you know spending money on a I
Want an X expert or serving expert or whatever?
And there are various
Systems you can use to like go in an X runtime and a wsh maker where you can kind of say
Here's my o in an X and or when it all serve it for you or whatever pi torch also has a mobile framework
same idea
So
All right, so you've got I mean it's kind of funny. We're talking about two different kinds of deployment here one is deploying like a
Hobby application, you know that you're prototyping showing off to your friends explaining to your colleagues how something might work
you know a little interactive analysis, and that's one thing or but maybe you're actually prototyping something that you're
Want to turn into a real product?
or an actual real part of your company's
operations
When you're deploying
You know something in in real life there's all kinds of things you got to be careful of
Sampling to be careful of is let's say you did exactly what we just did
Which actually this is your homework is to create your own
application and I want you to create your own image search application you can use
My exact set of widgets and whatever if you want to but better still
Go to the I pi widgets website and see what other widgets they have and try and come up with something cool
Try and comment, you know try and show off as best as you can and show us on the forum now, let's say you decided
that
You want to create an app that would help
The users of your app decide if they have healthy skin or unhealthy skin
So if you did the exact thing we just did rather than searching for grizzly bear and teddy bear and so forth on bing
You would search for healthy skin and unhealthy skin and so here's what happens, right?
if I and remember in our version
We never actually looked at being we just used the Bing API the Image Search API, but behind the scenes
It's just using the website. And so if I click healthy if I type healthy skin and say search
I actually discover that the definition of healthy skin is
Young white women
touching their face leveling
Lee, so that's what your your healthy skin classifier would learn to detect
right, and so
This is so this is a great example from Deborah G. And you should check out her paper actionable auditing
for lots of cool insights about model bias, but I mean here's here's like a
fascinating example of how if you weren't looking
at your data carefully
You you end up
With something that doesn't at all actually solve the problem you want to solve?
This is tricky right because
The data that you train your algorithm on if you're building like a new product that didn't exist before by definition
You don't have examples of the kind of data that's going to be used in real life, right?
So you kind of try to find some from somewhere and if there and if you do that throw it through like a Google search
Pretty likely you're not going to end up with
A set of data that actually reflects the kind of mix you would see in real life
So
You know the main thing here is to say be careful right and and in particular for your test set
You know that final set that you check on
really try hard to gather data that
reflects the real world so that Gus, you know, for example for the healthy skin example
You might go and actually talk to a dermatologist and try and find like ten examples of healthy and unhealthy skin or something
And that would be your kind of gold standard test
Um
There's all kinds of issues you have to think about in deployment I can't cover all of them
I can tell you that this O'Reilly book called building machine learning powered applications
Is is a great resource?
And this is one of the reasons we don't go into detail about
AP to a B testing and when should we refresh our data and we
monitor things and so forth is because that books already been written so we don't want to
Rewrite it
I do want to mention a particular area that I care a lot about though
Which is
Let's take this example
Let's say you're rolling out this bear detection system and it's going to be attached to video cameras around a campsite
It's going to warn campers of incoming bears. So if we used to model that was trained with that data that we just looked at
You know, those are all
Very nicely taken pictures of pretty perfect bears, right?
There's really no relationship
To the kinds of pictures. You're actually going to have to be dealing with in your in your
Campsite bear detector, which has it's going to have video and not images. It's going to be nighttime. There's going to be probably low resolution
security cameras
You need to make sure that the performance of the system is fast enough to tell you about it before the bear kills you
You know, there will be bears that are partially obscured by bushes or in lots of shadow or whatever
None of which are the kinds of things you would see normally in like internet pictures
So what we call this we call this out of domain data out of domain data refers to a situation where?
The data that you are trying to do inference on is in some way different
To the kind of data that you trained with
This is actually um, there's no perfect way to answer this question and when we look at
Really helpful ways to to
minimize how much this happens for example, it turns out that having a diverse team is a great way to
Kind of avoid being surprised by the kinds of data that people end up coming up with
But really is just something you've got to be super thoughtful about
Very similar to that is something called
The main shift and the main shift is where maybe you start out with all of your data is in domain data, but over time
The kinds of data that you're seeing
changes and so over time maybe
raccoons start invading your campsite and you
Weren't training on recurrence before it was just a bear detector
And so that's court domain shift and that's another thing that you have to be very careful of great choice or question
No, I was just gonna add to that in saying that
All data is biased so there's not kind of a, you know, a form of de bias data
Perfectly representative in all cases data and that a lot of the proposals around
Addressing this have kind of been converging to this idea and that you see in papers like Tim net get bruised
data sheets for datasets of just writing down a lot of the
Details about your data set and how it was gathered and in which situations it's appropriate to use and how it was maintained
And so there that's not that you've totally eliminated bias
but that you're just very aware of the attributes of your data set so that you won't be blindsided by them later and
there have been kind of several proposals in that school of thought which I which I really like around this idea of just kind of
Understanding how your data was gathered and what its limitations are
Thanks, Rachel
So a key problem here is that you can't know the entire behavior of your neural network
With normal programming you typed in the if statements and the loops and whatever
So in theory, you know, what the hell it does
Although it still sometimes surprising in this case you you didn't tell it anything. You just gave it
Examples alone from and hope that it learned something useful
There are hundreds of millions of parameters in all of these neural networks
And so there's no way you can understand how they all combine with each other to create complex behavior
so really like there's a natural compromise here is that we're trying to
Sophisticated behavior so stuff like like recognizing
pictures
Sophisticated enough behavior. We can't describe it
And so the natural downside is you can't expect the process that the thing is using to do that to be describable
View for you to be able to understand it. So
Our recommendation for kind of dealing with these issues is a very careful
Deployment strategy which I've summarized in this little graph this little chart here
the idea would be
first of all
Whatever it is that you're going to use the model for start out by doing it manually. So have a park ranger
watching for bears
Have the model running next to them and each time the park ranger sees a bear
They can check the morale and see like did it see into a pick it up? So the models not doing anything
There's just a person who's like running it and seeing would it have made sensible choices?
And once you're confident that it makes sense that what it's doing seems reasonable in
You know as being as close to the real-life situation as possible
Then deploy it in a time and geography limited way
so pick like one campsite not the entirety of California and do it for
you know one day and
Have somebody watching its super carefully, right? So now the basic bear detection is being done by the Baudette bear detector
But there's still somebody watching it pretty closely and it's only happening in one campsite for one day
And so then as you say like, okay
we haven't
Right our company yet
Campsites for a week and then let's do you know the entirety of Marin for a month and
so forth, so this is actually what we did when I
used to
Be at this company called optimal decisions
optimal decisions was a company that I found it to do insurance pricing and
If you if you change insurance prices by, you know, a percent or two in the wrong direction in the wrong way
You can basically destroy the whole company. Um, this has happened many times, you know insurers are companies
That set prices that's basically the product that they provide
So when we deployed new prices for optimal decisions, we always did it by like saying like, okay
we're going to do it for like five minutes or
Everybody whose name ends with a D, you know, so we kind of try to find some
Group, which hopefully would be fairly, you know
It would all be different
but not too many of them and would gradually scale it up and you've got to make sure that when you're doing this that you
have a lot of
Really good reporting systems in place that you can recognize
Are your customers yelling at you? Are your computers burning up?
you know are your
Are your computers burning up are your costs spiraling out of control and so forth so it really requires
Great
Reporting systems
This fast AI have methods built-in that provide for incremental learning ie improving the model slowly over time with a single data point each time
Yeah, that's a great question. So
this is a little bit different which is this is really about
Dealing with domain shift and similar issues by continuing to train your model as you do inference. And so the good news is
You don't need anything special for that
It's basically just a transfer learning problem. So
You can do this in many different ways. Probably the easiest is just to say like okay each night
probably the easiest is just to say ok each night you
Know at midnight
We're going to set off a task
Which grabs all of the previous day's transactions as many batches and trains another epoch
and
So yeah, that that actually works fine. You can basically think of this as a
Fine tuning approach where you're pre trained model is yesterday's model and you're fine-tuning data is today's data
So as you roll out your model
One thing to be thinking about super carefully is that it might change the behavior of the system that it's a part of
And this can create something called a feedback loop and feedback. Loops are one of the most challenging things for
for real world model deployment particularly of machine learning models
because they can take a
very minor issue and
Explode it into a really
big issue
so for example, think about a
predictive policing algorithm
It's an algorithm that was trained to recognize
You know basically trained on data that says whereabouts or arrests being made
And then as you train that algorithm based on where arrests are being made
Then you put in place a system that sends police officers to places that the model says
Are likely to have crime which in this case? Where were were there? Where were arrests?
Well, then more police go to that place
Find more crime because the more police that are there the more they'll see they arrest more people
Causing you know, and then if you do this incremental learning like we're just talking about that
It's going to say oh there's actually even more crime here. And so tomorrow it sends even more police
And so in that situation you end up like the predictive policing algorithm ends up kind of sending all of your police
or one street block
Because at that point all of the arrests are happening there because that's the only place you have policemen and I should say police officers
so there's actually a paper about
This issue called to protect and serve and in to protect and serve the author's right this really nice phrase
Predictive policing is aptly named it is predicting policing not predicting
crime so
if the initial model was
Perfect, whatever the hell that even means but like it's somehow sent police to exactly
The best places to find crime based on the probability of crimes actually being in place
I guess there's no problem, right?
But as soon as there's any amount of
Bias, right. So for example in the US
There's a lot more arrests
Of black people than of white people even for crimes where black people and white people are known to do than the same amount
So in the presence of this bias
or any kind of bias
You're kind of like setting off this domino chain of feedback loops where that bias will be
exploded
over time
So
You know one thing I like to think about is to think like well what would happen if this?
If this model was just really really really good
They were like who would be impacted?
You know, what would this extreme result look like how would you know what was really happening this incredibly predictive algorithm. That was like
Changing the behavior of yours if you're police officers or whatever, you know, what would that look like? What would actually happen?
And then like think about like, okay what could go wrong
And then what kind of rollout plan what kind of monitoring systems what kind of oversight?
Could provide the circuit breaker because that's what we really need here right is we need like nothing's going to be perfect. You can't
Be sure that there's no feedback. Loops
but what you can do is try to be sure that you see when the behavior of your system is behaving in a way that's
Not what you want
Did you have anything to add to that Rachel I?
Would add to that is that you're at risk of potentially having a feedback loop
Anytime that your model is kind of controlling what your next round of data looks like and I think that's true for pretty much all
products and that can be a
hard jump from people people coming from kind of a science background
Where you may be thinking of data as I have just observed some sort of experiment
Where is kind of whenever you're you know?
Building something that interacts with the real world
You are now also controlling what your future data looks like based on kind of behavior of your algorithm
For the current current round of data
right, so
So given that
You probably can't avoid feedback. Loops
the you know, the the thing you need to then really invest in is
the human in the loop, and so a lot of people like to focus on
Automating things which I find weird, you know, if you can decrease the amount of human involvement by like 90 percent
you've got almost all of the economic upside of automating it completely but you still have the room to put
Human circuit breakers in place. You need these appeals processes
You need the monitoring you need, you know humans involved to kind of go. Hey, that's that's weird
I don't think that's what we want
Okay
Yes, Rachel and just one more note about that those humans though. Do need to be integrated well with
Kind of product and engineering and so one issue that comes up is that in many companies? I think that
Ends up kind of being underneath trust and safety handles a lot of sort of issues with how things can go wrong
Or how your platform can be abused?
and often trust and safety is pretty siloed away from
Product and edge which actually kind of has the the control over, you know these decisions that really end up influencing them
and so that they the
Engineers probably considered them to be pretty pretty annoying a lot of the time how they get in the way and get in the way
Of them getting software out the door. Yeah, but like the kind of the more integration you can have between those
I think it's helpful for the kind of the people building the product to see
What is going wrong and what can go wrong if the engineers are actually on top of that?
They're actually seeing these these things happening that it's not some kind of abstract problem anymore
So, you know at this point now that we've got to the end of chapter 2
You actually know a lot more than most people about
about deep learning and actually about some pretty important foundations of machine learning more generally and if data products more generally
So there's a great time to think about
writing
So
Sometimes we have
Formatted text that doesn't quite format correctly interpret a notebook by the way, it only formats correctly in in the book book
So that's what it means when you see this kind of pre formatted text
So
The the idea here is to think about
Starting writing at this point before you go too much further Rachel
There's a question, okay, let's hit the question
Question is I am I assume there are fast day. I type ways of keeping a nightly updated transfer learning setup
Well, could there be one of the fasting for notebooks have an example of the nightly transfer learning training?
Like the previous person asks, I would be interested in knowing how to do that. Most effectively with fast AI
Sure, so I guess my view is there's nothing faster you guys specific about that at all?
So I actually suggest you read a manuals book that book. I showed you to understand the kind of the ideas
And if people are interested in this I can also point you with some academic research about this as well
And there's not as much as that there should be
But there is some there is some good work in this area
Okay, so
the reason we mentioned writing at this point in our journey is because
You know things are going to start to get more and more heavy more and more complicated and
A really good way to make sure that you're on top of it is to try to write down what you've learned
Sharing the right part of the screen before but this is what I was describing in terms of the pre-formatted text, which doesn't look correct
So
When so
Rachel actually has this great article that you should check out which is why you should blog and
I
Will say it's sort of her saying cuz I have it in front of me and she doesn't
weird as it is so rachel says
That the top advice she would give her younger self is to start blogging sooner
So rachel has a math PhD in this kind of idea of like blogging was not exactly something
I think they had a lot of in the ph.d program
But actually it's like it's a really great way of
Finding jobs. In fact, most of my students who have got the best jobs our students that have
good blog posts
The thing I really love is that it helps you learn
By by writing down. It's kind of synthesizes your ideas
and
Yeah, you know, there's lots of reasons to blog so there's actually
Something really cool. I want to show you. Yeah
As also just gonna note I have a second post called advice for better blog post
That's a little bit more advanced which I'll post a link to as well
and that
talks about some common pitfalls
that I've seen in many in many blog posts and kind of the importance of putting putting the time in to do it well and
And some things to think about so I'll share that post as well. Thanks, Rachel
um, so one reason that sometimes people don't blog is because it's kind of annoying to figure out how to
particularly because I think the thing that a lot of you will want to blog about is
Cool stuff that you're building and Jupiter notebooks. So
We've actually teamed up with a guy called Hamel sane and and with github to create this
free product
As usual with faster ie no ads, no anything called fast pages where you can actually blog
with Jupiter notebooks
So
You can go to fuss pages and see for yourself how to do it
But the basic idea is that like you literally click one button
Sets up a plug for you and then you dump your
notebooks
Into a folder called underscore notebooks and they get turned into
blog posts it's it's basically like magic and Hamill's done this amazing job of this and so
This means that you can create blog posts where you've got
Charts and tables and images, you know where they're all actually the output of you put a notebook
along with all the the markdown
formatted text headings and so forth and
Hyperlinks and the whole thing. So this is a great way to start writing about what you're learning about here
Something that Rachel and I both feel strongly about when it comes to blogging is this which is
Don't try to think about the absolute most advanced thing, you know and try to write a blog post that would impress
geoff hinton
Right because most people are not geoff hinton
so like a you probably won't do a good job because you're trying to like
log for somebody who's more got more expertise than you and
be
You've got a small audience now, right?
Actually, there's far more people that are not very familiar with deep learning than people who are so try to think, you know
And and you really understand what it's like
What it was like six months ago to be you because you were there six months ago
So try and write something which the six months ago version of you would have been like super
Interesting full of little tidbits. You would have loved you know that you would that would have delighted you
that six months ago version of you
Okay. So once again don't move on until you've had a go at the questionnaire to make sure that you
You know understand the key things we think that you need to understand
And yeah have a think about these further research questions as well because they might help you to engage more closely with material
So let's have a break and we'll come back in
five minutes time
MNIST
Yann Lecun
LeNet
MNIST sampleMNIST37
MNIST sample
untar_datauntar_datafastai
URL
URLs.MNIST_SAMPLEtab
path
.Path.BASE_PATH
path.ls
path
pathPathlibPath
Pathlibls
ls
?
fast corefast corefastai
PyTorch
pandas
?1
doc
ls
trainvalid
train
threes
threes1
im3
PILPython
PNG
Jupyter Notebook
PIL
array
The array is part of numpy which is the most popular
arraynumpynumpy
PIL
image object to array
array
Jupyter
arrayPILnumpy.array
numpy.array
so once I do this we can then index into that array and
arraytensortensor
numpy.arrayPyTorch
arraytensor
PyTorchtensornumpyarray
PyTorchtensor
GPU
numpy.arrayPyTorchtensor
numpy.arrayGPU
numpy
Python
PyTorchTensorNumPy
tensorarray
3tensor
im3_tim3tensorim3_t
pandas.DataFrame
background gradient
MNIST28x28768
How would you like you don't need to know anything about neural networks, or?
28x28
Jeremy
80%
85%
Python
sevens
Image.openPILtensor
Python
C#link
JavaScript
o
tensor
tensor7
Silvyan
3tensor1
tensorPIL Image
Jupyter
show_imagefastaitensor
tensortensor
tensor
three_tensors[1]
shape
(28, 28)three_tensors
28x28
3tensor
tensor
torch.stacktensor
stacked_threesshape
(6131, 28, 28)
So it's kind of like a cube of height 6 1 31
28x28
tensor
PyTorch
3axes123
33tensor
2tensor
tensorshape
axes
NumPyaxesPyTorchdim
ndim
tensor
shapetensor
stack_threes.mean()stack_threes.mean()
mean(0)
28x28
6131reduction
L1
L2
So, let's have a look let's take a three
dist_3_abs
0.1L1
L1
a3mean30.1
mean70.15
a3mean3
a3
mean73
l1_lossl1_loss
mse_loss
arraytensor
tensorarray
array
tensor
1:
Python
Right. So type is a function
Pythontype
tensortensorlong
floatfloat
NumPyPyTorch
valid
3ls
tensorstack
Okay
shape
is_three3True
mnist_distance
xy
a3mean3
0.114
mnist_distance
a3
mean3
3tensor
Python
GPUtensorPythonGPU
a - b
- b
valid_3_tensvalid_3_tens
1000mean3
shapetensor -
shapetensor
shapeshape
shape
1010mean3
mean3
13tensor
2shape
1, 2, 32, 1, 12, 3, 4
shape
1:36:32.700,1:36:38.329r
1010valid_3_tens1010mean3
mean31010
CCUDA
absolute valueshape(1010, 28, 28)tensor
abs
mean
-1-22
mean((-1, -2))2
is_three
3yes
floatyes1
Set right. So this is so cool. We basically get rid of loops
loop
In in in in this kind of programming you should have very few very very few. Loops. Loops make things
much harder to read
GPU
is_threevalid_three_tens
float
371 - 3
391%
798%95%
95%37
Machine learning. This is not something where there's a function which has some parameters
X
WW
1tensorW
step
So these seven steps 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
So, let's like
MNISTx
fastaiplot_function
f
x
-1.5
x2x
PyTorch
tensor
requires_grad_PyTorchtensor xt
You see the underscore at the end and
_
PyTorchin-place
requires_grad_
xtPyTorch
xt
3tensor
ff39
backward
requires_grad_xt
x2x
x3
backward.grad
PyTorch
31tensor
(3, 4, 10)
sum()
f
f(xt)
backward()(2x, 2x, 2x)
Khan Academy
Correspondingly, that's what a slope is
w
0.0011
And so the way I did this was I just grabbed a range just grabs
arange
The numbers from naught up to but not including 20, right? So these are the time periods at which I'm taking my speed measurement and
Then I've just got some
9.50.751
We guess that it's a function a times x squared plus B times time plus C
tB t + C
You might remember from school is quite a quadratic
So let's create a function, right? And so
Let's create it using kind of the Alpha Samuels technique the machine learning technique. This function is going to take two things
It's going to take an input
a, b, c
Python
PyTorch
f
backwardgrad2
10-5
- x
data attribute
PyTorchdata
fdata attribute
5400-300
backward
notebook
So let's now apply this to em mist
MNIST
/
(y_new - y_old) / (x_new - x_old)
x_newx_old
x=0
MNIST
1web
Rachel
web
ipywidget